We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Let’s see if you know more about
basic nutrition than most doctors.
Here’s our first story.
A poor diet now outranks smoking
as the leading cause of death
on the planet, as well as
specifically in the United States.
In the US, the #1 killer of Americans
is the American diet.
So, if diet is humanity's #1 killer,
then obviously it's the #1 thing
taught in medical school, right?
Sadly, medical students around the
world are poorly trained in nutrition.
It's not that medical students aren't
interested in learning about it.
Medical schools just
aren't teaching it.
Without a solid foundation of clinical
nutrition knowledge and skills,
physicians worldwide are generally
not equipped to even begin to have
an informed conversation about
nutrition with their patients.
How bad is it? One study assessing
the clinical nutrition knowledge
of medical doctors found the majority
got 70% of the questions wrong.
And they were multiple
choice questions,
so they should have gotten about
a fifth right just by chance.
And the wrong answers were not limited
to dificult or demanding questions.
For example, less than half could
guess how many calories are in
fat, carbs and protein; only 1 in 10
knew the recommended protein intake;
and only about 1 in 3 knew
what a healthy BMI was.
I mean, this is like super
basic nutrition knowledge.
And what's worse, not only did
the majority of medical doctors
get a failing grade, but 30% of those
who failed had a high self-perception
of their clinical nutrition expertise,
meaning not only were they clueless
about nutrition, they were also clueless
that they were clueless about nutrition,
a particularly bad combination
given that doctors are trusted
and influential sources
of healthy eating advice.
For those majority of consumers
who get information
from their personal health care
professional, 78% indicate making
a change in their eating habits
as a result of those conversations.
So if everything the doctor knows they
read in some checkout aisle magazine,
that's what the patients
are going to be following.
Only a quarter of doctors
surveyed correctly identified
the American Heart Association's
recommended number
of fruit and vegetable servings
per day, and fewer still
were aware of the recommended
daily added sugar limits.
So how are they going
to counsel patients on it?
Yet again, of the doctors who perceived
themselves as having high nutrition
knowledge, 93% couldn't answer those
two basic multiple-choice questions.
Physicians with no genuine
expertise in, say, brain surgery
are neither likely to broadcast
detailed opinions on that topic,
nor have their "expert
opinions" solicited by media.
And most topical domains in
medicine enjoy such respect;
we defer expert opinion and
commentary to actual experts.
Not so with nutrition, where the
common knowledge that physicians
are generally ill trained in this area
is conjoined to routine invitations
to physicians for their expert
opinions on the matter.
All too many are willing to provide
their opinions, absent any basis
for actual expertise, or worse, made
on the basis of bias and personal
preference, sometimes directly tethered
to personal gain such as diet book sales.
That's one of the reasons all the
proceeds I receive from my books
are donated directly to charity.
I didn't even want the appearance
of any conflicts of interest.
In a culture that routinely fails to
distinguish expertise from mere opinion
or personal anecdote, we physicians
should be doing all we can
to establish relevant barriers to entry
for expert opinion on diet and nutrition,
as in all other matters of
genuine medical significance.
I mean, we're not talking
celebrity gossip.
Lives are at stake, and there
are entire industries devoted
to marketing messages
that may conspire
directly against well-informed
medical advice in this area.
Medical education must
be brought up to date.
For physicians to be ill trained
in the very area most impactful
on the rate of premature death
at the population level
is an absurd anachronism. The
mission of medicine is to protect,
defend, and advance
the human condition.
That mission cannot be
fulfilled if diet is neglected.
Maybe one place to
start is for physicians
and health care organizations
to collectively begin to emphasize
their seriousness about
nutrition in health care
by practicing what they at
least should be preaching.
Is it appropriate to serve pizza and
soft drinks at a resident conference
while bemoaning the high
prevalence of obesity
and encouraging patients
to eat healthier?
A similarly poor example exists
in medical conferences,
including national meetings,
where some morning sessions
are accompanied by foods
such as donuts and sausage.
About a decade ago, the American Heart
Association expressed concern
that their “2020 target of improving
cardiovascular health by 20 percent
by 2020 [would] not be reached
if current trends continue[d].”
By 2006, most people were
already not smoking,
and had nearly achieved
their goal for exercise.
But when it came to healthy diet
score, only about 1 percent
got a 4 or 5 out of their
0 to 5 diet quality score,
and that’s with so-called
“ideal” criteria of like drinking
less than four and a half
cups of soda a week.
In the last decade they
saw a bump up to like 1 percent
of Americans even reaching
those kinds of basic criteria.
But given their aggressive goal
of improving that by 20 percent
by 2020, they hoped to turn that
1 percent into about 1.2 percent!
Okay, so how’d we do?
Let’s look at the 2019 update,
and it looks like we’ve slipped
down to as low as one in a thousand—
you can’t even see the green anymore.
And American teens got a big fat zero.
No wonder, perhaps, that “for all
mortality-based metrics, the U.S.
rank declined … 27th or 28th
among 34 [industrialized] countries.”
“Citizens living in countries
with a substantially lower [GDP]
and health expenditure[s]
per capita . . . have lower
mortality rates than those
in the United States.”
Slovenia beat us by three
countries, coming in at 24th
in life expectancy to our 27th.
And more recently we seem to have
slipped to 43rd, even
though we spend trillions
on health care—more than anyone else.
What’s the leading risk factor
for death in the United States?
What we eat. The standard American
diet is just to die for—literally.
Those trillions in health care spending
aren’t addressing the root cause.
“Approximately 80 percent of
chronic disease and premature death
could be prevented by not
smoking, being physically active,
and adhering to a
healthful dietary pattern.”
But what exactly is
meant by “healthy diet”?
Unfortunately, what we hear
about nutrition in the media
is often inconsistent and confusing.
“There[’s a] pressure
within today's competitive
journalism market for sensationalism.
There may even be a disincentive
to present the facts in … context…”
to sell more magazines.
In fact, about three-quarters
of a century ago it was noted
that unfortunately, “the subject
of nutrition seems to have
a special appeal to the
credulous, the social zealot
and, in the commercial field,
the unscrupulous,” a combination
“calculated to strike
despair in the hearts
of the sober, objective scientist.”
“The most important [health care]
problem [we face may be]
our poor lifestyle choices
based on misinformation.”
It’s like the climate change deniers;
“healthy … dietary advice
[is] overshadowed by critics,
diet books, [industry interests],
and misguided information
in the media.”
Maybe what we need is
like an IPCC (Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change) of nutrition.
These days “[n]o single expert,
regardless of academic stature
or reputation, has the prominence
to overcome the obstacles
created by confusing media
messages and [effectively] deliver
the fundamental principles of
healthy living … to the public.”
However, what if there was
“a global coalition consisting
of a variety of nutrition experts,
who collectively represent
the views held by the
majority of scientists,
physicians, and health practitioners…”?
It could “serve as the guiding
resource of sound nutrition information
for improved health and
prevention of disease.”
Boom! “The True Health
Initiative was conceived
for that very purpose.” A nonprofit
coalition of hundreds of experts
from dozens of countries
agreeing to a consensus statement
on the fundamentals of healthy living.
Check out
https://www.truehealthinitiative.org/.
Spoiler alert—the healthiest diet
is one generally comprised
mostly of minimally processed plants.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.